<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
/*
 *                  Eoulsan development code
 *
 * This code may be freely distributed and modified under the
 * terms of the GNU Lesser General Public License version 2.1 or
 * later and CeCILL-C. This should be distributed with the code.
 * If you do not have a copy, see:
 *
 *      http://www.gnu.org/licenses/lgpl-2.1.txt
 *      http://www.cecill.info/licences/Licence_CeCILL-C_V1-en.txt
 *
 * Copyright for this code is held jointly by the Genomic platform
 * of the Institut de Biologie de l'École normale supérieure and
 * the individual authors. These should be listed in @author doc
 * comments.
 *
 * For more information on the Eoulsan project and its aims,
 * or to join the Eoulsan Google group, visit the home page
 * at:
 *
 *      http://outils.genomique.biologie.ens.fr/eoulsan
 *
 */
-->
<document>

<properties>
  <title>Command line and configuration files</title>
  <author email="jourdren@biologie.ens.fr">Laurent Jourdren</author>
</properties>

<body>


    
  <section name="The command line">

  <p>The only user interface of Eoulsan is the command line. The syntax and the
  available options can be get using the following command :</p>
<source>
$ eoulsan.sh -h
</source>

  <p>The program show you the following output:</p>

<source>
usage: eoulsan [options] action arguments
 -about                display information about this software
 -conf &lt;file&gt;          configuration file to use
 -h,--help             display this help
 -j &lt;path&gt;             JAVA_HOME path
 -J &lt;args&gt;             JVM arguments (-server by default)
 -license              display information about the license of this
                       software
 -log &lt;file&gt;           external log file
 -loglevel &lt;level&gt;     log level
 -m &lt;size&gt;             maximal memory usage for JVM in MB (4096 by default)
 -p &lt;classpath&gt;        additional classpath for eoulsan plugins
 -s &lt;property=value&gt;   set a configuration setting. This option can be
                       used several times
 -version              show version of the software
Available actions:
 - emrexec      execute eoulsan on Amazon Elastic MapReduce service.
 - createdesign create a design file from a list of files.
 - createhadoopjar      create a jar file for hadoop with all dependencies include.
 - exec execute Eoulsan in local mode.
 - hadoopexec   execute Eoulsan on local hadoop cluster.
</source>


  <p>Actually, Eoulsan has 5 available actions:</p>
  <ul>
    <li><b>emrexec</b>: Upload data and launch Eoulsan analysis on Amazon Web Services cloud.</li>
    <li><b>exec</b>: Launch Eoulsan analysis in local mode.</li>
    <li><b>hadoopexec</b>: Launch Eoulsan analysis on a Hadoop cluster.</li>
    <li><b>createdesign</b>: Create a design file from a list of fastq, gff and fasta files.</li>
    <li><b>createhadoopjar</b>: Create an Eoulsan jar file that contains all jar dependencies. This jar file can be used to run manualy Eoulsan on a Hadoop cluster (local or in Amazon Web Services cloud).</li>
  </ul>

  <p>You can display general help and specific help about an action using <b>-h</b> argument.</p>

    <subsection name="-about">
      <p>When you run Eoulsan with this option, you will get information about Eoulsan authors and then returns to the shell.</p>
    </subsection>
    <subsection name="-conf &lt;file&gt;">
      <p>With this option, Eoulsan will load the <b>file</b> as configuration file. See the <a href="conffile.html">configuration section</a> for more information.</p>
    </subsection>
    <subsection name="-s &lt;property=value&gt;">
      <p>With this option, Eoulsan will set a specific setting. Usage of this option override settings loaded in configuration file. Key and value of the setting are separated by the '=' character.
         This option can be used several times in command line. See the <a href="conffile.html">configuration section</a> for more information.</p>
    </subsection>
	<subsection name="-j &lt;path&gt;">
		<p>This option allow to define the path to the JVM to use for running Eoulsan.</p>
	</subsection>
	<subsection name="-J &lt;args&gt;">
		<p>Define the JVM options when running Eoulsan. The default value is "<b>-server</b>".</p>
	</subsection>
    <subsection name="-license">
      <p>When you run Eoulsan with this option, you will get information about Eoulsan license and and then returns to the shell.</p>
    </subsection>
    <subsection name="-log &lt;file&gt;">
      <p>Define the log file.</p>
    </subsection>
    <subsection name="-loglevel &lt;level&gt;">
      <p>Set the log level, there are 5 log level define in Eoulsan : <b>Severe</b>, <b>Warning</b>, <b>Info</b>, <b>Fine</b> and <b>all</b>. By default the log level is set to <b>Info</b>.</p>
    </subsection>
	<subsection name="-m &lt;size&gt;">
		<p>Define the maximal size in megabytes that can be allocated by the JVM. The default value is <b>4096</b>.</p>
	</subsection>
	<subsection name="-p &lt;classpath&gt;">
		<p>Define additional classpath for Eoulsan plug-ins or dependencies.</p>
	</subsection>
    <subsection name="-version">
      <p>When you run Eoulsan with this option, you will get information about Eoulsan version and then Eoulsan returns to the shell.</p>
    </subsection>
  </section>

    <section name="Environment variables">

        <p>In order to avoid modify the <tt>eoulsan.sh</tt> file, you use the following  environment variable to configure Eoulsan JVM and plugins path:</p>
        <ul>
            <li><b>EOULSAN_JAVA_HOME</b>: The path to the JDK to use with Eoulsan. If this environment variable is not set the <b>JAVA_HOME</b> environment varibale will be used. If none of this environment variables is set, the default java command will be used to launch Eoulsan.</li>
            <li><b>EOULSAN_MEMORY</b>: The maximum size in MiB of the JVM memory allocation pool. Default value is 4096.</li>
            <li><b>EOULSAN_JVM_OPTS</b>: The JVM options. Default value is "-server".</li>
            <li><b>EOULSAN_PLUGINS</b>: The path to Eoulsan plugins. No default value is set.</li>
        </ul>


    </section>


</body>
</document>
