<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- 
/*
 *                  Teolenn development code
 *
 * This code may be freely distributed and modified under the
 * terms of the GNU General Public License version 2 or later. This
 * should be distributed with the code. If you do not have a copy,
 * see:
 *
 *      http://www.gnu.org/licenses/gpl-2.0.txt
 *
 * Copyright for this code is held jointly by the microarray platform
 * of the École Normale Supérieure and the individual authors.
 * These should be listed in @author doc comments.
 *
 * For more information on the Teolenn project and its aims,
 * or to join the Teolenn Google group, visit the home page
 * at:
 *
 *      http://www.transcriptome.ens.fr/teolenn
 *
 */
-->
<document>

	<properties>
		<title>Quickstart</title>
		<author email="lecrom@biologie.ens.fr">
			Stephane Le Crom
        </author>
	</properties>

	<body>

		<section name="Quickstart Guide">

			<ul>
				<li>
					<a href="#installation">Installation</a>
				</li>
				<li>
					<a href="#firstrun">Probe library creation</a>
				</li>
				<li>
					<a href="#stats">Probe library statistics and filters</a>
				</li>
				<li>
					<a href="#selection">Final probe selection</a>
				</li>
			</ul>


			<a name="installation"/>
			<subsection name="Installation">


				<p> To install Teolenn, go to the
					<a href="installing.html">Teolenn installation page</a>
					and follow the detail procedure.
				</p>
			</subsection>


			<a name="firstrun"/>
			<subsection name="Probe library creation">


				<p>Create a folder where to put all your files. Next in this folder download
				the genome reference file (fasta format) and the masked genome (fasta format).
				</p>

				<p>Create your design file (xml format) either from scratch using the 
				<a href="design.html"> documentation pages </a> or by using the 
				<a href="./design-thricoderna-reesei.xml">template design file</a> we provide.
				The better is to create the design file in the same folder than genome files.
				</p>
				<p>In the design file first edit the general parameters. Choose the start position
				between 0 or 1. This is important because this will help you make the link with annotations
				files. Choose the length of the oligonucleotide you want to design. Then fill
				the relative location to the design file for your genome files.
				</p>
				<p>Next edit the sequencefilters and measurements. Pay attention that both values
				of the "skip" parameter is set to "false". We advise to use both the redundancy and
				Sequencexn filters. For the measurement you can add oligosequence, tm, %gc, complexicity and unicity.
				If you don't know which parameter to provide for maxprefixlength you can let it
				set to 30.
				</p>
				<p>For measurementfilters and selector you can set the "skip" parameter to
				"true". Then launch the teolenn program for example as follow.
				</p>
		 	  <source>$ sh ../teolenn/teolenn.sh -log design.log design.xml</source>

			</subsection>

			<a name="stats"/>
			<subsection name="Probe library statistics and filters">


				<p>This first run has created the whole probe collection and apply a first 
				general filter to discard redudant oligonucleotides and non classical bases.
				You can now access the statistics of all the parameter calculated for the 
				probe collection in the "filtered.stats" file. This file display each parameter
				in column with an histogram distribution of the values and max, min, mean,
				median and standard deviation calculated.
				</p>
				<p>These value are helpful to set up threshold on probe collection to discard
				low quality probes. To do so open the design.xml file. First put the skip
				parameter of sequencefilters and measurements to "true". Next edit the 
				measurementfilters section and first put the skip value to "false".
				For each measurement you can edit threshold based on the statistical 
				distribution obtained.
				</p>
				<p>Now, you can launch teolenn another time. The probe collection is already 
				done so that only the probe filtration step will be performed. This step is 
				now very quick. At the end you can access the number of probe remaining in
				the filtered.mes file to compared with the number of oligonucleotide in the
				collection found in the oligo.mes file.
				</p>

			</subsection>

			<a name="selection"/>
			<subsection name="Final probe selection">


				<p>Now that you have filtered your probe library according to your needs, 
				the final step is to perform the probe selection. To do so edit the 
				design.xml file and put all skip tag to true except for the last one 
				(selector). Only the selection step will be done each time you will launch
				Teolenn so that you can test several selection parameter configurations.
				</p>
				<p>For a tiling design add "tiling" to the "name" tag and set the two
				parameters specific for this design: windowLength and windowStep. The
				first give the size of the tiling window. The second give the step of 
				the tiling path.
				</p>
				<p>Next set up the weight of each of the parameter to be taken into 
				account for the final score calculation. Then launch the program. The final
				design probe can be retrieved in the select.mes file.
				</p>

			</subsection>

		</section>
	</body>
</document>

